Hi I'm Ty Brown with dogbehavioronline.com.
I'm here in Riverton, Utah today teaching you how to train a dog.
The topic of today's discussion is teaching your dog how to come when called.
Now one of the most frustrating things that dog owner complain to me about is that their dogs don't come when called.
And so it's really important, not only to have a dog that doesn't run away, but to have a dog that can come in a time that maybe car is coming or something like that.
It's important that the dog comes when called.
And so the tool that you're going to need is what's called a long-line.
Now a long-line is just a 20 foot leash typically made out of cotton.
What you're going to want to do is get your dog away from you.
Maybe 10, 20 feet.
Give the dog's name and then the command.
And then immediately following the command just a little tug on the leash as you trot backwards.
You trotting backwards is going to give that dog a bit of a target to go to.
And the second he comes to you you're going to praise him heavily and make him feel very good about what he's done.
Do this with a lot of repetition.
And now you don't have to tug very hard, but we just want something physical associated with that word 'come'.
Now if you do this a thousand times let's say, time number one thousand and one now you don't have the leash on, you give the command.
"Rocko come."
And sure enough, because you've done it so many times it's hard-wired into the dog's head and even without the leash here he comes.
And he comes running.
So using these techniques is what's going to teach your dog how to come when called.